Guide to the Landor Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Landor papers
1838-1880
OSB MSS 23
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.04
(3 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence and other manuscripts principally relating to the financial and familial troubles of Landor's last years. Letters from his niece Elizabeth Sophia Landor to Robert Browning discuss Landor's affairs in detail and Browning's attempts to assist his friend in Florence; Landor's letters to his children Walter, Julia and Charles present his view of the family's struggles. Other correspondents include his friend and admirer Rose Paynter; Richard Monckton Milnes; and Luizinha O'Donnell. The collection also contains approximately 300 manuscript fragments by Landor, including drafts of letters, short poems, statements concerning his legal affairs, and memoranda.
Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
WALTER SAVAGE LANDOR, 1775-1864
Walter Savage Landor was educated at Rugby School and Trinity College, Oxford, from which he was sent down in 1794 after firing a gun at the windows of a fellow-student. In the course of a long and frequently unsettled life, Landor published poetry, criticism, travel works and memoirs, and is now principally remembered for the prose dialogues Imaginary Conversations (1824-1853).
Landor was acquainted with some of the notable literary figures of his time, including Charles Lamb, William Hazlitt, Leigh Hunt, Charles Dickens, Robert Southey, and John Forster, but both his literary and his personal relationships were often marked by quarrels and difficulties. He married Julia Thuillier in 1811; the Landors and their growing family lived in Florence until 1835, when Landor separated from his wife and returned to England. In 1857, after a series of legal and financial entanglements culminated in a costly libel judgement against him, Landor fled back to Florence, where he made several unsuccessful attempts at residing with his family before he was eventually settled in an apartment by Robert Browning and given an allowance by his brothers at Browning's request. In the last year of his life, he was visited by Algernon Charles Swinburne, who dedicated his "Atalanta in Calydon" to him. Landor died in Florence on September 17, 1864, survived by his four children.
Scope and Contents
The Landor Papers contain correspondence and other material principally relating to the financial and family difficulties of Landor's later years. The papers span the dates 1838-1880 and have been organized into two series: I. Correspondence; and II. Other Papers.
Series I, Correspondence, is housed in Boxes 1-2 and contains alphabetically arranged letters to and by Landor and other family members. The letters from Landor to his children, located in folders 48-54, present his view's of the family's quarrels and their financial burdens, while the letters of Elizabeth Sophia Landor discuss Landor's problems and Browning's attempts to assist him in Florence. Other correspondence includes many brief social notes from his friend and admirer Rose Paynter and business letters from several advisors.
Series II, Other Papers, is housed in Boxes 2-3. Folders 84-99 contain a variety of fragments in Landor's late hand, many of them apparently quotations from his own work or attempts at versification. Other material includes genealogical notes and a partial description of some items in the collection.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Families -- England -- Domestic relations; Fathers and daughters; Inheritance and succession; Boyle, Carolina Courtenay; Browning, Robert, 1812-1889; Hare, Augustus J. C. (Augustus John Cuthbert), 1834-1903; Milnes, Richard Monckton, Baron Houghton, 1809-1885; Landor, Arnold Henry Savage, 1865-1924; Landor, Elizabeth Sophia; Landor, Julia Elizabeth Savage; Landor, Robert Eyres, 1781-1869; Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864; O'Donnell, Luizinha; Paynter, Rose; Thuillier, Lucy
- Correspondence, Series I
  - BALDELLI, GERTRUDE (WALKER), COUNTESS
    - 4 ALS to W. S. Landor, Florence, 1863-64 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Concerning Landor's health and his
      writing desk.
  - BEVAN, WILLIAM
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., 6 Old Jewry, 1865 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      With draft of reply by W. S. Landor,
      Jr., on p. 4. Concerning legal
      action about legacy.
  - BLOXHAM, THOMAS LAWRENCE, 1798-1880
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Rugby, 1863 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - BOROUGH, E C. (Gawen)
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Newport, Shropshire, 1858 Sep 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BOYLE, CAROLINE COURTENAY
    - 2 ALS (both incomplete) to W. S. Landor, Portishead, Bristol, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - BRICKMANN, CHRISTOPHER DEAKE
    - 4 ALS to W. S. Landor, Bath and Paris, 1858-63 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Concerning the Yescombe trial.
    - 4 ALS to W. S. Landor, Bath, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      With 2 drafts of replies by
      Walter Savage Landor, Jr.
  - DUKE, ELLEN SAVAGE (LANDOR), 1819-
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Church Eaton, 1864 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Church Eaton, 1865 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      With draft of reply by W. S.
      Landor, Jr.
  - DUKE, ROBERT RASHLEIGH, 1818-
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Church Eaton, 1864 Aug 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - EDWARDS, JOSEPH
    - ALS to C. S. Landor, Hutton, 1883 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 5 ALS to W. S. Landor, Hutton, 1865 Mar-Nov (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - EMPSON, CHARLES, D. 1861
    - ALS to [Col. Edward Stopford], Bath, 1861 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes messages for W. S. Landor.
  - FIELD, MARY KATHERINE KEEMLE, 1838-1896
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Nonantrun Hill, 1862 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - FRENCH, A.
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., 36 Bury St., St. James's, 1865 Oct 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - GARRETT, HENRY
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Bath, 1858 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - HARE, ANNE FRANCES (PAUL)
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Hotel (?) Charles, Victoria, 1858 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - HARE, AUGUSTUS JOHN CUTHBERT, 1834-1903
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Holmhurst, 1864 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - HARRIS, SARAH
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, New York, 1862 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Introduces Mrs. Ellet.
  - HOUGHTON, RICHARD MONCKTON MILNES, 1ST BARON, 1809-1885
    - ALS to Charles Landor, Basel, 1883 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 3 ALS to W. S. Landor, 16 Upper Brook St., 1865 Mar (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Includes invitations and a
      suggestion to call on Swinburne in
      Belgravia; the third letter
      contains a draft of Landor's
      reply.
  - JAMES, E. N.
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, [Bath], [1856] (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - KIRKUP, SEYMOUR STOCKER, 1788-1880.
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Florence, 1858 Oct 24 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - LANDOR, ARNOLD SAVAGE, 1818-1871
    - ALS to Julia (Thuillier) Savage Landor, London, 1842 Jun 9 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, [n.p.], 1853 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - LANDOR, ELIZABETH SAVAGE, 1776-1854
    - ALS to A. S. Landor, Warwick (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - ALS to Julia Landor, Warwick, 1852 Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 2 ALS to W. S. Landor, Warwick, 1848, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - LANDOR, ELIZABETH SOPHIA, 1816-
    - 29 ALS to R. Browning, Tachbrooke, 1859-64 (Box 1, Folder 29-34)
      Enclosed in No. 21 is ALS by W. S.
      Landor.
    - 3 ALS to W. S. Landor, Tachbrooke and Bath, 1858-64 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Tachbrooke, 1864 Dec 22 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Concerning details of W. S.
      Landor's will.
  - LANDOR, HENRY EYRES, 1780-1866
    - ALS to Arnold S. Landor, Warwick, 1835 Dec 28 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Warwick, 1854 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Concerns approaching death of
      Elizabeth Landor.
  - LANDOR, JULIA ELIZABETH SAVAGE, 1820-1884
    - 2 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Florence, 1865 Mar, Sep (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - LANDOR, ROBERT
    - 7 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Rugeley, 1865 Mar, Aug (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - LANDOR, ROBERT EYRES, 1781-1869
    - 3 LS to Robert Browning, Birlingham, 1864 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Concerns Browning's kindness with
      W. S. Landor's effects.
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, Birlingham, 1852 Jun (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - LS to W. S. Landor, Tachbrooke, 1864 Jul 5 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      In the hand of Sophy Landor.
    - Letter to W. S. Landor, Jr., Birlingham, [1865] Sep 8 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - LANDOR, WALTER SAVAGE, 1775-1864
    - Copy of 3 letters to William Allingham, Bath, 1850, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - ALS to Robert Browning, Rugeley, 1860 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - 13 ALS to Arnold Landor, [v.p.], 1838-ca. 1860 (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
    - 7 ALS to Charles Landor, [v.p.], [1851-1860] (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Letter (copy, in Italian) to C. S. Landor, [Florence], 1863 Aug (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - 22 ALS to Julia Landor, [v.p.], 1843-60 (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
    - 22 ALS to Walter Landor, Jr., [v.p.], 1849-60 (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
    - 2 AL (drafts) to Rose Paynter, [n.p.], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - NAPIER, SIR WILLIAM FRANCIS PATRICK, 1785-1860
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, [Bath], 1857 Dec 31 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - O'DONNELL, LUIZINHA (PEREIRA DE SODRE)
    - 12 ALS to W. S. Landor, Baltimore, 1852-64 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - PAYNTER, ROSE
    - ALS to Julia Landor, [n.p.] (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - 98 ALS to W. S. Landor, [v.p.], 1838-61 (Box 2, Folder 59-67)
      Chiefly short civility notes,
      including one from her infant
      daughter, Rosina.
  - PAYNTER, SOPHIA (TWEED), 1790-1863
    - 4 ALS to W. S. Landor, [n.p.], [1842-45] (Box 2, Folder 68)
      One letter enclosed a lock of Rose
      Aylmer's hair (not present).
  - SANDFORD, WILLIAM GRAHAM
    - 4 ALS to W. S. Landor, Genoa Bath, 1858-63 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - SHEPPERD, EMILY
    - ALS to Edward Stopford, [London], [1850 May] (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - SHOUBRIDGE, CHARLES
    - ALS to Mr. de Tivoli, 1 Lincoln's Inn Fields, 1867 Jan 28 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - SHOUBRIDGE, HARRY
    - 5 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., 1 Lincoln's Inn Fields, 1865 Oct-Nov (Box 2, Folder 72)
      Concerns financial affairs of the
      Landor family.
  - STOPFORD, EDWARD
    - 5 ALS to W. S. Landor, London and Madrid, 1850-61 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      Letters concern family matters and
      several refer to Stopford's
      daughter, Theresa (Lady Charles
      Beauclerk), and her family. Letter
      has a post script by Mrs. Stopford.
  - STOPFORD, LAURA (THUILLIER)
    - ALS to C. S. Landor, Richmond, [ca. 1860] (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - 5 ALS to W. S. Landor, [v.p.], 1855-62 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - 5 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Richmond and London, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - 2 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Richmond and London, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - STORY, EMELYN (ELDREDGE), D. 1894
    - ALS (incomplete) to W. S. Landor, [Rome], [1863] (Box 2, Folder 78)
      Refers to Civil War in the United
      States.
  - THUILLIER, LUCY
    - 2 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., [n.p.], [1864] (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - TWISLETON, EDWARD TURNER BOYD, 1809-1874
    - 3 ALS to W. S. Landor, 3 Rutland Gate, London, 1863-64 (Box 2, Folder 80)
      Personal and literary gossip.
  - WALKER, ARTHUR DE NOE, FL. CA. 1820-1870.
    - ALS to W. S. Landor, [n.p.], 1863 Feb 25 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - WEST, MRS. FREDERICK (WHITBY)
    - 3 ALS to W. S. Landor, Lymington and Italy, 1863-64 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - WHITEHOUSE, E.
    - 2 ALS to W. S. Landor, Jr., Ipsley, 1865-66 (Box 2, Folder 83)
      Legal affairs of Landor estate.
- Other Papers, Series II
  - MANUSCRIPT MATERIAL BY LANDOR
    - Epitaph fragments in Latin, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Grammatical humor fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 85)
    - Italian fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 86)
    - Latin fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 87-88)
    - Letter drafts, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 89)
    - Literary personages fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 90)
    - Prose fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 91-93)
    - Verse fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 94-96)
    - Miscellaneous fragments, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 97-99)
    - Autograph request, 1858 Apr 17 (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Empty envelopes and visiting cards (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - BIBLIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
    - Bibliographic publications, 1967, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Genealogical material, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103-104)
    - Original descriptive material, 1963, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 105)